all right that has concluded the live
presentations section of the
Symposium I'm now going to play the
pre-recorded videos so one second to
rearrange get it in
position now we'll continue with the
pre-recorded
videos hopefully all of them
concatenated into the next few hours
okay this talk is by Leonardo MOA
Rodriguez Groove as the musical glue for
social
bonding ladies and gentlemen hello
welcome to today's talk on Groove as a
musical glue for social bonding my name
is Leonardo Mula Rodriguez I'm a PhD
student at Center and this is a
neuroscientific and crosscultural
perspective now I'm a bit self-conscious
by the fact that the only audio you'll
be hearing today is my voice no music
but do books sing No we're doing a deep
dive into the scientific literature not
musical theater maybe musical theater in
the future of uh my active
inference why my my name is Lear Müller
Rodriguez I'm a PhD student at the
Cambridge Institute for music therapy
Research Center and my focus is on sleep
music four dimensions and if you cous
how does this tie in with danceability
where it relates to musical entrainment
U more specifically slow beats I'm also
a composer music produc producer and
musician so how this groove Foster
social bonding there's a little outline
of today's presentation Groove and his
relationship to Spotify stability the
Neuroscience of it the social bonding
the crosscultural aspect flow States in
music what musical features Define
Groove an active inference application
of GrooVe and a l update to
Spotify uh suggestion so what is Groo in
essence it's the Apex of an inverted
u-shape relationship between rhythmic
complexity and grooviness so and
pleasure if you uh
grooviness is at a moderate level of um
rhythmic complexity which is um rhythmic
complexity is if you use the musical
term syncopation is the amount to which
the Rhythm deviates from the meter or
the beat
or alternatively you can think of um the
tempo the beat is a Tempo and it relates
to how certain you have your predictions
of that Rhythm so Groove is a
pleasurable sensation sensation of
wanting to move the body to music driven
by rhythmic patterns that balance
predictability and surprise here's
another study looking at the same thing
and we'll see into the Neuroscience in a
bit that proves this now spotify's
danceability is a measure they use and
they Define it as so we don't have the
the actual computation that they do it's
the suitability of a track for dancing
based on a combination a unknown
combination unless you work at Spotify
of tempo Rhythm stability beat strength
or pulse Clarity and overall regularity
and this data sets um someone put this
on on reddits and they've looked at a
million tracks and like okay you beat me
in terms of data set um and so they've
categorized all the musical genres
several musical genres in terms of uh as
a function of dance ability and based on
the discussion and it makes sense um on
Reddit it's more about rhythmic
Simplicity seems to analyze because it's
more more danceable music is techno deep
house and then you have salsa music
which is lower and people in the
comments who are salsa Dan like what
what is going on and especially metal
heavy Rock or hard you know metal fans
that were thinking like wait is comedy
more dancable than my favorite wrer so
they're a bit offended with that um at
least sleep music makes sense that it's
kind of low um yeah so it lacks this
relationship between the complexity and
predictability fun fact if you listen to
all the million tracks it will take you
7 years and 9 months if you listen to it
on 24/7 basis here's my data set I
compared sleep soundtrack sleep
playlists um that are either very
popular on YouTube or that I've created
my own self or playlist that I have
millions of subscribers on Spotify to
high energy music such as gy music that
has this beast mode playlist has a mill
11 million uh subscribers so this regon
uh music regon is a Latin popular dance
music very popular 11 million and this
has about 5 million and you see the
dance ability is in general higher for
this higher energy music compared to
sleep music and here I compared
veillance and high energy music is also
more positive apparently uh sleep music
is more negative anyway let's dive into
the Neuroscience of it and here the main
thing I want you to focus on is the fact
that b
perception is present in the brain and
uh frequencies increase their strength
at the onset of the pulse here there are
different temp that were used or
different speeds uh between pulses and
as you see there's always an increase
just after the uh pulse regardless of
the tempo it happens all the time and it
happens at the level of beta and Alpha
brain waves and gamma brain waves these
higher brain uh frequencies higher
frequencies and um it activates these uh
brain regions here and we'll go a bit
more in detail but it seemed it's quite
wide range and it turns out that we can
call these the musical Rhythm brain
Network because it makes use of the
damic and rhythmic sorry the doer mintic
reward system in the brain um for beat
perception and positive effect of groovy
music and this involves a supplementary
motor area premotor area nearby the pmen
as well as for pleasure and the urge to
move to the music is the nucleus acaban
and this connection to the medial
orbital frontal cortex because we're
talking about an auditory stimulus um
auditory regions must be involved and uh
the cereum also form fine motor
movements turns out that musical Rhythm
predictions and surprises are measurable
in the bra in the brain on in two forms
so the first one is about short-term
habituation to a rhythm via repetition
of a certain Rhythm and then the
deviation from that the surprising
change to that rhythm is seen here in
this paper where this this measure
called the mismatch negativity which
measures prediction errors in relation
to Rhythm deviations changes or Omission
that you don't have that note that used
to be in that
Rhythm and the other form um of
surprises and predictions is by the
recruitment of long-term memory or uh we
can talk about it in terms of implicit
music theory syntactic knowledge where
here regardless of you're being told in
advance that there will be a
non-traditional chord sequence um that
will be played you will have this sort
of mismatch negativity which is more
specific because it recruits long-term
memory here is called the electric
respon in the auditory nerve era and um
yes that's an interesting aspect um by
traditionally I mean traditional music
western music theory um for harmonies
here again we just looking a bit deeper
into this whereby beta waves we saw
earlier and gamma waves The High
Frequency waves we saw earlier in terms
of beat perception are responsible for
top down so the beliefs the predictions
better and the updating the surprises um
through the gamma high frequency
um activity in the brain
so another aspect of of music is that
it's usually done in groups such as
musical performance um appreciation
music therapy or learning about music
and turns out that music in groups
synchronizes brains and this is called
interpersonal brain synchrony and in
addition it recruits the same musical
Rhythm Network that we just saw with a
you know a bit more broadening of it it
has the amygdalin insula which is
usually involved visceral um uh activity
and more generally the prefrontal cortex
the Moto areas uh you know could involve
actually moving if you're performing and
the basil gangli in general which
incorporates all the dopaminergic reward
system which nuclear acents uh and
dopaminergic system Etc putam in Cate we
saw that
earlier now music the real function of
Music beyond the auditory cheesecake
that Stephen Pinker says
it's not just pleasure not just reward
systems it has to do with social bonding
and building trust music is a
participatory um activity and dancing
actually is a way to
participate without any musical
virtuosity or even familiarity to the
music this is why I call it embodied
Democratic music participation open to
all and fosters joy and social
bonding and music strengthens
this interact uh interactive rituals you
can talk about it in terms of ritual and
it's a social tool for enhancing uh
groups so as as you can see here you
start to predict you the Beats you see
repetitive motions this induces Groove
induces dancing to it and this enhances
social bonding within this sort of you
can frame it within an agent environment
system
more of a uh seeing others uh dance and
move encourages dancing so this
reinforces the social bonding aspect and
this was examplified here where eyes
open uh with low Tempo High Tempo High
roof actually increases
the collective movement um in a group of
people listening to music and this is
what they were measuring here with this
cross
wavelet
and uh dance promotes also here
interpersonal movement interaction
promotes self other integration it
enhances social cohesion through
synchronized movements and more
specifically
moderate uh syncopation and low as well
for Al there an implication for parkon
disease low and moderate syncopation
which is groovy
music um does so as well it
encourages self other
inclusion Which social B and now we're
talking about music The Groove and is it
applicable to a crosscultural uh
definition of Music well first there has
been this is with Japanese music
actually there has been an optimal
Groove Tempo range identified um which
seems to be a u inverted u-shape
relationship non linear relationship
with Tempo is this seems to be from 107
to
126 B BPM beats per minute uh Tempo and
The evolutionary interpretation for this
is the fact that it's near 120 BPM which
is the optimal tempo for walking and
dancing so this is where Groove might
come into sensory motor synchronization
is most optimal in that around 120
BPM um and there are also universals
crosscultural universals of Music which
has been identified using statistics
um and the main aspects that are
crosscultural is Beats dancing making
music in group percussion repetitive
melodic sequences these are musical
features that are Universal just going a
bit deeper into this they used a music
for all around these spots it's quite a
geographically varied data set although
only 34 recordings you know there's
millions of music but I think it's a
nice General generalization we make
based on the Black Box the black box
here are musical features that are at
least
50% uh shared in globally and the most
uh which are the most you know the
whiteness as is
shared um the most share of the beat
subdivisions by binary tary subdivisions
or scales that have up to seven notes so
this is interesting and this was
controlled phenetically meaning that
this ensure that the these musical
patterns and associations are not solely
due to Shared cultural or evolutionary
histories another aspect that is
crosscultural are musical bodily
Sensations and emotions what I want you
to focus on here is this correlation
they asked um Asian participants 5 500
people and Western participants 500
people to associate emotional labels to
musical features and there's a very
strong correlation
094 uh between these so there's a sort
of crosscultural aspect here obviously
it's not all cultures maybe African
Latin and uh Middle Eastern cultures
do feel differently but here's just a
Latin um influence that's indeed
instrumental sinking in syn pated music
which is uh groovy music which here was
Samba um encourages the urge to dance
so Groove at least is present in Latin
American music now musical flow is not
restricted to groove what is flow flow
is a state of absorption total
absorption in an activity in other words
the feeling of losing yourself in the
moment uh flow state is usually
characterized as a state of emotional
resilience against traa
and here emotional expressivity is one
of those not Groove uh uh musical
features that induces musical flow and
here the two uh main things I want you
to focus on is the blue um histograms
which are state of flow here were
performers piano performers and this is
a musical feature and so there was
higher flow during swelling dynamics of
crescendos that
which is volume um uh
fluctuations as well as um
repetition of um
Melodies and not only just any Melodies
but stepwise Melodies that are not too
far apart in terms of distance on the
keyboard uh or in terms of notes so the
closer they are blue is again flate the
closer they are the The Melodies the
more flow and juicing
they
provoke um another musical element that
provokes flow that is not Groove is the
narrative Arc storytelling emotional
Journeys in music and this interesting
paper by colleague Annie hesit
identified stages emotional stages of
the heroes Journey which is a a
narrative Arc found in myths films
popular films yeah in stories narratives
in general they've identified emotional
stages of the hero's journey in patients
and clients specifically in this case
was eating disorders but applying to
just more
generally undergoing music therapy so
most they were look they were doing
guided imagery with music which is a
type of music therapy
and depending what they're saying the
clients these themes were identifiable
within this uh the heroes Journey
narrative Arc so that's very interesting
um and this is very important for music
therapists because this uh informs
further the scanning aspect that they
usually do in
gim which is that they try to identify
using the music where is the emotional
stage that the client and the therapist
should start their um work emotional
work and so this is actually a emotional
Journeys are actually a concept that is
applied by DJs they usually talk about
energy arcs for their DJ sets um and
it's also very prevalent in film
soundtracks um you know film
soundtracks are using so music is being
used to guide the emotional journey of
the
audience
now flow as neural
entrainment I think it's neural
entrainment is evident for beat
perception we've seen it several times
here's more evidence like accurate beat
perception increases neural entrainment
here is just saying that beat
sensitivity uh there's a sort of tempor
range where this sensory motor
synchronization decreases uh with very
slow Tempe um but here again be
perception this the beat is being um
being identified in a neural activity
and even if you imagine certain rhythms
these frequencies appear also in the
brain activity so neuron training with
beat perception is clear but how about
for emotional expressivity and um
emotional Journeys well this
study um reconstructed the music that
was listened to by the uh participants
from their neural patterns it was a
combination of EG and fmri a technique
that made use of EG and fmri and and
deep neural networks to reconstruct the
music based on the neural
activity and you can see that not only
very impressively resembles quite a lot
in terms of spectrogram information but
obviously there's not just Rhythm
activity or yeah Rhythm information
that's being displayed there's more
there's frequency activity
so this takes us to this study that
demonstrated that spectral flux is
actually the most um
accurate measure for neural entrainment
to music and you can see this with this
red line is the highest
correlation um and with neural
entrainment and in addition they've uh
demonstrated that it is a metric that
encompasses amplitude Envelope as well
as beats they they have mutual
information here and spectral flux or
spectral novelty is called is a measure
me of Novel energy increases in the
frequency
spectrum um so this an interesting
aspect now nevertheless as you can see
other strong neural synchronization
musical
features um in addition to spectral flux
are Tempo range so uh roughly as you can
see here with the orange uh line 60 to
120 BPM uh High familiarity with the
music and post CL wey to perceive the
Beats so let's keep it simple what are
the groove's musical features two things
moderate rhythmic complexity within an
optimal range of around the walking
tempo of humans
um this these two Encompass most of
these characteristics syncopation Tempo
micro timing event density this has to
do with and even beat sence has to do
with rmic complex complex soap of attack
is a variant of beat saliency a low
frequency band is the base enhances um
dancing uh volume and then this is the
core progression and that now keep in
mind that sensory motor synchronization
is not limited to this uh Groove Tempo
range the sensory motor uh
synchronization Tempo range is shown to
be between 60 to 180 BPM below Above
This the sensory motor synchronization
which is usually finger tapping or
dancing to the beat decreases um which
is probably linked to biomechanical
reasons um however probably training
increases your capacity to do so uh to
synchronize however the beat perception
still can occur Beyond those uh temp
this Tempo
range uh I recommend watching this
YouTube video by Adam NE which uh goes
into this uh the extremes of be
perception let's apply active inference
into Groove but first before we do that
we need to understand that the brain is
constantly generating predictions about
how the world Works in order to minimize
the uncertainty about how the world
Works two the brain is a lay thing and
it balances top down and bottom up
influences
where higher layers send beliefs about
the world down to lower sensory layers
which the sensory layers as we can see
here um actually send back up sensory
stimuli to adjust the uh beliefs through
the mechanism of minimization of
prediction errors or minimization of
free
energy now talk about groove groove
balances confid
prediction uh confident predictions with
surprise about the Rhythm uh just
reminding you it is an optimal playing
with belief updating about musical
rhythms now listening to groove is
accessible to groups of people and
therefore can become a shared stimulus
for motor and emotional synchrony and
therefore under the active inference uh
framework
um generates generalized
synchrony uh which
means that people have shared World
models the listeners have shared World
models
and this is depicted
here um uh with this quote it say
neither a model of my behavior or your
behavior but a model of our Behavior
quote by
friston
um and generalized synchrony actually
requires flexibility in terms of your
higher uh
beliefs um and because you're trying to
model uh flexibly your Collective
identity and Collective behavior and
because of this and the social bonding
aspect I place musical groove on the
spectrum of the Rebus hypoth hypothesis
which is a relaxed belief under
psychedelics meaning that it's not as
the the flattening of the free energy
landscape is not as Extreme as
psychedelics are supposed to do but
musical Groove can achieve this through
the the social
bonding so dancing to the same music not
only increases trust and social bonding
but it also allows for individual
creativity compare an expert dancer and
a novel dancer um a novice dancer and an
expert won't be having motor mimicry but
they will be sharing emotional s
and this uh provides the mechanism for
trust and
bonding while considering uh creativity
of individuals and you can make use of a
Federated belief multi-person system um
to
model
Groove as the shared marginal likelihood
that people nonverbally
communicate um so because idiosyncratic
dance moves have been shown to even
increase more uh the social bonding and
Trust I encourage you next time to take
the risk and bust on some moves on the
on the dance for all right so what are
what I want you to consider right now
is the current models of the context
that encourages dancing yes they say
musical properties they have temporal
predictions that you can do induces
pleasure induces arousal and
together with regularity Chris urged to
move to the
music and um this will generate motor
planning or policy generation under the
active inference uh framework and and
this desire to move and in training um
body movements creat social connection
but I like to add a bit more to this in
terms of contextual factors based on the
literature review we're presenting today
this is a hypothetical contextual Factor
um framework for dance ability um
basically Groove is the mechanism for uh
dancing but there are several contextual
layers that people individuals might
need to cover um before starting to
dance for instance I have two example
individuals a white individual here this
white uh Arrow who requires um seeing
other people seeing their friends to
before starting to move whereas this red
individual just requires to feel a
change in emotions to start wanting to
move and these layers uh have a
nonlinear relationship with the group
meaning that uh your entry level
contextual entry level to start dancing
um might be seeing a friend starting to
dance and you might not need familiarity
with the music to start dancing to start
connecting to the groove
uh whereas DJs sometimes make use of
familiar music in their DJ sets to
encourage people to start dancing they
say getting those first three people to
dance is always the most difficult part
and uh once you have them the crowd
joins and you have a crowd dancing so
this was modeled with a reduction of
entropy to do it relatively simply uh
whereby depending on the distance to the
groove there's a higher um entropy level
that has a nonlinear relationship
uh with
grooving and K has is based on
personality and the relationship between
each
layer there's another way of
conceptualizing this as a the gravity of
GrooVe the layers uh are done like this
so implications for spotify's
danceability we saw that is more likely
has to do with rhythmic complexity
comedy is more dancable than
uh Blues apparently or or heavy metal
headbanging is not as you know dancing
as as
laughing veence as well the most joyful
music seems to be as Sala and the less
joyful music is sleep maybe Spotify is
inspired by uh the rapper Nas who has a
lyric saying sleep is a cousin of
death so let's go beyond this and uh and
uh on Rhythm and Tempo and incorporate
what we've been seeing today into dance
ability so if you want to generate the
formula that goes beyond theability
unkknown equation which is most likely
rithmic Simplicity we
convert uh we Sorry first uh I want to
point you to this study which asked
musicians to perform groovy music uh
with simple and complex M Melodies and
they show that there's about 30%
occurrence of fast notes uh specifically
16th notes um when people perform groovy
music and this was also confirmed in
terms of listeners saying yeah that's
groovy um and so here I've just uh used
the optimal Groove range and transformed
it into seconds so you can have an idea
and ah too quick for Spotify they can't
no I'm just kidding uh you get to see
the the the equation um so what I've
done is I made use of uh spectral flux
which is this spectral novelty makes use
of for transform and then logarithmic
compression to enhance uh weakened
spectral components and then you compute
the difference between time frames in
terms of positive energy
increases and so the measures positive
increases in Energy Event density is
another measure that's been used in
these studies and it's a number of
events onsets per a Time window so
here's a Groove uh formula I suggest
which is open to to your feedback um
which is 30% of energy
onsets uh that is in the 16th of a note
um time
window um divided by a
measure that's dependent on the tempo
and a measure is four times a beat
because most music is on 4x4 meter music
so I want to give you this quote dance
is an energetic mode of participation
for a large population regardless of age
familiarity with music or instrumental
singing
virtuosity to summarize we found that
Groove is a musical mechanism for social
bonding through movement and therefore
through movement is danceability right
and we can make use of the active
inference to model grp as a musical
mechan mechanism for generalized
synchrony even uh as Federated beliefs
to um model individual creativity
further Works um would encourage the
usage of uh um other social bonding
metrics in music such as group
singing uh chanting is seen around
rituals around the world and this has
implications for group music therapy
life performances and team building
music recommend assist sys Etc so please
do comp contact me I'm open to
collaborate for this uh Groove um
projects and discuss any of your ideas
uh we could discuss about musical uh uh
you know exchange music if you want and
I just want to show here my YouTube
channel which explores thanks to the
YouTube channel I've actually learned
how active inference works you know they
say teaching is the best way of
memorizing and in here for instance I
made explored Chris Field's um work in
the active inference with the
holographic
boundary um for social interactions
which is which could also be a a further
uh direction of of trying to to
conceptualize musical Groove in that
manner but shared marginal likelihood is
probably very effective as well uh thank
you so much please do ask me for the
references um I will send them they have
been sent or yeah I should be on the
chat by way asking answering some
questions thank you very much for your
time see you very soon byebye thanks